<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>Roger Oba</title><description></description><link>https://roger.ml</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 1 Mar 2021 02:42:13 -0300</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Mon, 1 Mar 2021 02:42:13 -0300</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://roger.ml/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://roger.ml/posts/first-post</guid><title>"Hello, World!" Right?</title><description>This marks the first post written in this new website. Which means I'm finally migrating off of Medium. Hooray! 🎉</description><link>https://roger.ml/posts/first-post</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>"Hello, World!" Right?</h1><p>This marks the first post written in this new website. Which means I'm finally migrating off of Medium. Hooray! 🎉</p><p>"But why?" - you might ask. And it's a fair question. After all, why would anyone leave a free platform that makes publishing content so easy?</p><h2>Overall Look'n'Feel</h2><p>Medium is a writing platform made for everyone. But mostly write about programming topics, and Medium's UI isn't tailored for programming posts. Here I have full control over how the website will look like, how syntax highlighting will display different programming languages, I can format images any way I want, there's built-in dark mode support, etc - I get to choose how everything looks, and I can change it at any point in time.</p><p>In Medium, simply posting a multiline code snippet is cumbersome, since it has to first be uploaded to a GitHub gist.</p><h2>Content Ownership</h2><p>Here I own the data. No, really. Medium makes it easy for you import content into it, but exporting is painful. <a href="https://medium.com/@macropus/export-your-medium-posts-to-markdown-b5ccc8cb0050">There are some workarounds</a>, but I'd much rather own and store the content myself.</p><h2>Other Relevant Reasons</h2><p>There are <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Journalism/comments/8j7xly/why_do_people_love_to_hate_medium/">tons</a> <a href="https://yanngirard.typepad.com/yanns_blog/2015/10/why-you-shouldnt-blog-on-medium-.html">of</a> <a href="https://florimond.dev/blog/articles/2019/05/why-i-dont-write-on-medium/">articles</a> explaining why you shouldn't be blogging on Medium. I agree with most of them, specially as a developer. Worth checking those links.</p><h1>What Now?</h1><p>I'll migrate some of the Medium articles over to this website - only the relevant ones.</p><p>I might delete them from Medium after migrating them. This is because maintaining a copy of the content in two places is too costy. One way or another one of them gets auto of sync and starts causing issues.</p><p>You can follow me on Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/rogerluan_">@rogerluan_</a>) to be notified when a new post comes out here. Or you can subscribe to this website's RSS feed, if you're not on Twitter!</p><p>I'm looking forward to using this new <em>medium</em> (pun intended) to publish my content. 🥳</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>